Finding Aid for Ralph Waldo Gerard papers, 1922-1974
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ralph Waldo Gerard papers 1922-1974
Gerard, Ralph Waldo (1900-1974).
2 linear feet
9804 Aa 2
Neurophysiologist, founder of University of Michigan Mental Health Research Institute, also faculty member at University of Chicago, University of Illinois, and University of California, Irvine. Writings of R. W. Gerard, 1922-1973, including war research, 1942-1944, bibliography, and biographical material.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection (donor no. 8529 ) was transferred in September 1996 from the Mental Health Research Institute which had received the material from James W. Gerard, the son of Ralph Waldo Gerard.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Ralph Waldo Gerard, neurophysiologist, behavioral scientist and educator, was born in Harvey, Illinois on October 7, 1900. Gerard graduated from high school in 1915, from the University of Chicago with a B.S. degree in chemistry in 1919 and was awarded a Ph.D. in physiology by the University of Chicago in 1921. Gerard began his teaching career as head of the departments of physiology, biochemistry, and pharmacology at the University of South Dakota, 1921-1922. He headed the department of physiology at Hahnemann Medical College in Philadelphia, 1922-1924, and received his M.D. degree from Rush Medical College in Chicago in 1924. After working with A.V. Hill at University College, London in 1925-1926 and with Otto Meyerhof at the Kaiser Wilhelm Institute in Berlin in 1926-1927, Gerard returned to the United States and joined the faculty of the University of Chicago. By 1942 he had risen to the position of professor of physiology and neurophysiology, a position he held until 1952.
During World War II Gerard directed special military research at the University of Chicago and in 1945 was the civilian in charge of the physiological aspects of chemical warfare experiments at Edgewood Arsenal, New Jersey. From 1952 to 1955 Gerard was professor of neurophysiology and director of laboratories at the Neuropsychiatric Institute of the College of Medicine, University of Illinois. Gerard helped to found the Mental Health Research Institute at the University of Michigan where he became a professor of neurophysiology in the departments of physiology and psychiatry in 1955. In 1963, during a sabbatical from the University of Michigan, Gerard was visiting professor at the University of California, Irvine. He joined the fledgling university in 1964 serving as professor of biological sciences and director of special studies. He was appointed dean of the graduate division in September 1964 and served in that position until his retirement in 1970. In 1955 Gerard was elected to both the American Academy of Arts and Sciences and the National Academy of Sciences. Ralph Waldo Gerard died February 17, 1974.
References: Gerard, Ralph W(aldo), in Current Biography, May 1965, 21-23.
The Ralph Waldo Gerard papers consist primarily of the writings of Ralph Gerard from 1922 through 1973. The papers were received by the University of Michigan Mental Health Research Institute (MHRI) from James W. Gerard and were subsequently transferred to the University of Michigan archives at the Bentley Historical Library. When the papers were received they were in chronological order with evidence that most individual articles had been disbound from bound volumes. The collection is arranged into three series: Biographical Material, Bibliography, and Writings.
Subjects:
Gerard, R. W. (Ralph Waldo), 1900-1974; Neurophysiology.; World War, 1939-1945--Science.; Mental health.; University of Michigan. Mental Health Research Institute.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Gerard, R. W. (Ralph Waldo), 1900-1974
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical Material
  The Biographical Material series includes a paper from an autobiographical talk, "Some Comments at Seventy," and biographical articles, obituaries and memorials.
  - Autobiographical Talk, "Some Comments at Seventy," October 10, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Biographies 1965-1968 (Box 1)
  - Memorials and Obituaries 1974 (Box 1)
- Bibliography
  The Bibliography series includes a bibliography with complete citations covering Gerard's writings from 1922 through 1973. This bibliography appears to have been created by Ralph Waldo Gerard and is organized into genres of writings such as "Scientific Reviews," "Books," and "Popular Science and Lectures" and subject areas such as "Nerve-Heat and Chemistry" and "Nerve-Electrical." A chronological list of writings, created by MHRI staff, serves as a means of accessing the writings. Also included is a draft introduction and table of contents to what was once the bound compilation of writings.
  - Bibliography 1922-1973 (2 copies)
    - Copy 1 (Box 1)
      (Annotated with cross-listed numbers referring to the chronological list of writings created by MHRI staff to correspond to the physical location of the disbound papers)
    - Copy 2 (Box 1)
      (List of writings in chronological order, 1922-1968 prepared by Anne C. Davis, annotated with cross-listed numbers referring to the bibliography which includes complete citations)
  - Draft of introduction and table of contents to 4 volume compilation of writings 1973 (Box 1)
- Writings
  Items in the Writings series have been kept in the order in which they were received by the Bentley Historical Library--a chronological order as indicated on the chronological list. However, both the MHRI chronological list and the bibliography have been cross-indexed (by numbers) to each other. If a researcher is searching for a particular book review, for instance, the researcher should consult the bibliography under book reviews. The cross-listed number will refer to the chronological MHRI list that corresponds to the physical order of the writings. If a researcher is interested in writings from a certain time period, the researcher should refer to the MHRI chronological list and follow the referring number to the bibliography where complete publishing information will be found.
  - 1922-1932
    - Numbers 1-10, chronological list (Box 1)
    - Numbers 11-20, chronological list (Box 1)
    - Numbers 21-30, chronological list (Box 1)
    - Numbers 31-41, chronological list (Box 1)
    - Numbers 42-51, chronological list (Box 1)
    - Numbers 52-72, chronological list (Box 1)
  - 1932-1938
    - Numbers 73-89, chronological list (Box 1)
    - Numbers 90-105, chronological list (Box 1)
    - Numbers 106-127, chronological list (Box 1)
  - 1938-1942
    - Numbers 128-139, chronological list (Box 1)
    - Numbers 140-158, chronological list (Box 1)
    - Numbers 159-182, chronological list (Box 1)
  - 1942-1944
    - Bound volume, "War Research 1942-1944" (Box 1)
  - 1942-1947
    - Numbers 186-202, chronological list (Box 1)
    - Numbers 203-212, chronological list (Box 1)
    - Numbers 213-224, chronological list (Box 1)
    - Numbers 225-261, chronological list (Box 1)
  - 1948-1952
    - Numbers 271-290, chronological list (Box 1)
    - Numbers 291-307, chronological list (Box 1)
    - Numbers 308-337, chronological list (Box 1)
    - Numbers 338-383, chronological list (Box 1)
  - 1953-1957
    - Numbers 372-388, chronological list (Box 2)
    - Numbers 389-449, chronological list (Box 2)
    - Numbers 452-470a, chronological list (Box 2)
  - 1957-1962
    - Numbers 472-499, chronological list (Box 2)
    - Numbers 501-520, chronological list (Box 2)
    - Numbers 521-544, chronological list (Box 2)
    - Numbers 545-569, chronological list (Box 2)
  - 1963-1972
    - Numbers 570-580, chronological list (Box 2)
    - Numbers 581-588, chronological list (Box 2)
    - Numbers 599-631, chronological list (Box 2)
  - Undated
    - "Some of the Problems Concerning Digital Notions in the Central Nervous System," corrections of draft undated (Box 2)
Related Material
Related material held by the Bentley Library concerning Gerard, including photographs, may be found in the records of the University of Michigan Mental Health Research Institute (call number 9676 Bimu/2).
Additional material is available in other repositories. One folder of items related to R. W. Gerard is held by the University of Chicago. The University of California at Irvine holds the bulk of the Ralph Waldo Gerard papers: 104 linear feet and, as of December 1997, an additional 25 linear feet of unprocessed materials. The collection number is MS-F 6. Contact information: Special Collections UCI Libraries, P.O. Box 19557, University of California, Irvine, CA 92623-9557; telephone, 714/824-7227 or via e-mail reference at: spcoll@uci.edu.